Finding Aid for Charles David Williams Papers 1878-1923
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Charles David Williams papers 1878-1923
Williams, Charles David, 1860-1923.
3 linear feet
86339 Aa 2
Bishop of the Michigan Diocese of the Episcopal Church, 1906-1923, and advocate of the "social gospel" views of Walter Rauschenbusch. Papers consist of correspondence, notebooks on labor and social issues, and biographical material.
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the donation of Williams' daughters, Mrs. Allen Brett and Mrs. William S. McCormick (donor no. 4331 ) and came to the library in 1966.
The collection is open for research.
Charles David Williams was born July 30, 1860 in Bellevue, Ohio. He was educated at Kenyon College and Bexley Theological Seminary at Kenyon where he was ordained deacon in 1883 and priest in 1884 in the Episcopal Church. Williams served in different Ohio communities: as priest of Fernbank and Riverside (1884-1889); as deacon at St. Paul's in Steubenville (1889-1893); and as dean of Trinity Cathedral in Cleveland (1893-1906). In 1906, he was called as bishop of the Michigan Diocese of the Episcopal Church where he served until his death in 1923.
In his religious and social views, Williams was a liberal clergyman in the mold of Walter Rauschenbush. Williams believed that the church should play an active role in resolving social problems. Although convinced that the church would always need to minster to individual philanthropic causes, he argued equally vigorously that the established denominations, in their teachings and advocacy of basic principles, should support reform of the economic and industrial system that many saw as the root of the ills of the day.
Through his writings and addresses, Williams became internationally, known attending several of the Lambeth Conferences meeting in London. He was a member of the commission of church leaders that investigated the steel industry. He was national president of the Church League for Industrial Democracy. And in 1921, he attended a seminar in England that studied the English labor movement in its relation with the church.
Williams died February 14, 1923.
The collection has been brought together in the following series:
Biographical Materials, Box 1
Correspondence, 1878-1923, Box 1
Sermons, 1883-1923 and undated, Box 1-2
Lectures, Box 2
Journals, 1896-1921, Box 2
Events, 1904-1920, Box 2
Obituaries, Condolences, etc., 1923, Box 3
Various, 1905-1923 and undated, Box 3
Photographs, 1860-1920, Box 3
The papers of Charles D. Williams, Episcopal bishop of Michigan, include correspondence concerning personal and church affairs and the social gospel movement, including correspondence with Walter Rauschenbush, Samuel Mather, and Lucretia Garfield; also sermons and addresses, 1885-1923, journals of European trips, 1896, 1917, and 1921, notebooks on social and labor problems, material on the 1908 forest fire at Metz, Michigan (Presque Isle County), and material on the Trinity Cathedral, Cleveland, Ohio in 1898; biographical writings by his sons, Benedict Williams, his wife Lucy V. Williams, and his secretary, Charles O. Ford; letters of condolence from fellow clergy, including Reinhold Niebuhr; also photographs.
Subject Terms:
Clergy--Michigan.; Cleveland (Ohio); Eddy, Sherwood, 1871-1963.; Episcopal Church. Diocese of Michigan.; Europe.; Forest fires--Michigan--Metz.; Labor--Michigan.; Metz (Mich.); Michigan--Church history.; Sociology, Christian.; Voyages and travels.; Trinity Cathedral (Cleveland, Ohio); Williams, Charles David, 1860-1923.; Europe--Description and travel.
Form and Genre:
Diaries.; Photographs.; Sermons.
Contributors:
Ford, Charles O.; Garfield, Lucretia Rudolph, 1832-1918.; Mather, Samuel, 1851-1931.; Niebuhr, Reinhold, 1892-1971.; Rauschenbusch, Walter, 1861-1918.; Williams, Benedict.; Williams, Lucy V.
Subjects - Visual Materials
Churches--Ohio.; Clergymen.; Episcopal Church.; Ohio--Churches.; Williams, Charles David, 1860-1923.; Williams, Lucy V.; World War, 1914-1918.
- Biographical Material
  The Biographical Materials series consists of the different biographies (some intended for publication) written by Williams' wife Lucy V. Williams, his son Benedict Williams, and his secretary Charles O. Ford.
  - Biography of Charles D. Williams written by C. O. Ford, 1923 (Box 1)
  - "A sketch of the life of Charles D. Williams" written by Lucy B. Williams (Box 1)
  - Biography of Charles D, Williams written by son Benedict E. Williams, circa 1930 (Box 1)
  - Biographical volume compiled by family members (Box 1)
    (includes typed excerpts of selected CDW correspondence
  - Biographical/personal miscellanea (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series dates from 1878 to 1923, and concerns personal and church affairs. Of note is the correspondence with Walter Rauschenbush, December 12, 1916, January 17, 1917, and November 18, 1918. There are also letters from Samuel Mather, December 13 and 31, 1892, and from Lucretia Garfield, February 3, 1906. Letters written from northern Michigan in October 1908 recount the forest fire at Metz, Michigan. Many of the letters are from Williams written to his family while traveling aboard or away from home on church business in Michigan.
  - 1878-1923 and undated, 15 folders (Box 1)
- Sermons
  The Sermons series has been arranged by date (when known). If undated, individual sermons have been arranged by title or scripture verse on which the sermon was based. Most of these sermons are handwritten. A small portion of them have been published.
  - By date
    - Lent (Mark 6:31) February 18, 1885 (Box 1)
    - January 8, 1891 (Box 1)
    - Mark 6:31 February 11, 1891 (Box 1)
    - Matt. 5:3; The First Beatitudes March 16, 1892 (Box 1)
    - Sermon preached at Trinity Cathedral, Cleveland, Ohio October 31, 1897 (Box 1)
    - The Equal Right of All Men to the Use of the Earth February 23, 1898 (Box 1)
    - The Ministry of Reconciliation - 2 Cor. 5:18-20 December 11, 1898 (Box 1)
    - The Story of Joseph: A Drama of Providence July 2, 1899 (Box 1)
    - Psalms 100:16 1900 (Box 1)
    - Hebrews 1:14 September 30, 1900 (Box 1)
      (also Oct. 1, 1905)
    - John 2:25-26a April 13, 1901 (Box 1)
    - Eternal Life; John 17:3 May 1902 (Box 1)
    - The Shadow of Peter or Unconscious Influence; Acts 5:15 June 8, 1902 (Box 1)
    - Christmas Day Christmas 1902 (Box 1)
    - Luke 2:40 January 4, 1903 (Box 1)
    - The Joy of Service; Matt. 25:23 May 3, 1903 (Box 1)
    - Experience; They way into the Confidence of a Certain Faith; John 9:25b October 1903 (Box 1)
    - The Cloud of Witnesses. Heb. 12:1-2b November 1, 1903 (Box 1)
    - The Wise Men and Shepherds December 27, 1903 (Box 1)
    - The Chemistry of the Spirit; John 3:8 May 22, 1904 (Box 1)
    - Impedimenta; Hebrews 12:1 July 1904 (Box 1)
    - A Valid Christianity for Today, Church Club of Louisiana April 5, 1905 (Box 1)
    - [Untitled] 1906 (Box 1)
    - The Bible and the Word of God September 30, 1906 (Box 1)
    - First Annual Address delivered at the 73rd annual convention of the Episcopal Church November 14-15, 1906 (Box 1)
    - Annual sermon of the Churchmen's Union for the Advancement of Liberal Religious Thought 1908 (Box 1)
    - Visit to the University of Chicago November 21, 1909 (Box 1)
    - The Composite of the Modern Minister. Fifth Anniversary of his Consecration February 7, 1911 (Box 1)
    - "To me to live is Christ," Sage Chapel, Cornell University November 5, 1911 (Box 1)
    - Sermon at the Consecration of All Souls Memorial Church, Washington, D.C. October 25, 1914 (Box 1)
    - A Charge to 84th Convention of Diocese of Michigan in Christ Church May 23, 1917 (Box 1)
    - The War as a Day of Judgment. February 7, 1918 (Box 1)
    - St. John's Episcopal Church September 28, 1921 (Box 1)
    - The Fellowship of the Mystery May 16, 1922 (Box 1)
    - Ordination Sermon for Orville E. Watson Ordination, Gambier, Ohio June 18, 1922 (Box 1)
    - Last sermon preached February 11, 1923 (Box 1)
  - By title or scripture verse
    - Acts 5:15b (Box 1)
    - Amos (Box 1)
    - The Bible; Have we lost it? (Box 1)
    - A Cathedral Pilgrimage (Box 1)
    - Christianizing the Social Order (Box 1)
    - I Corinthians 12:4 & 7 (Box 1)
    - The Democracy of the Kingdom (Box 1)
    - Faith is the Substance of Things Hoped for, the Evidence of Things Unseen (Hebrews 11) (Box 1)
    - An Easter Message (Col. 3:1-4) (Box 1)
    - First Canonical Sermon Exegetical (Matt. 25:1-13) (Box 1)
    - The Followers of Jesus (John 12:19b) (Box 1)
    - Hiding in the Stuff or The Invasion of Leadership (Box 2)
    - Intelligence & Religion (Box 2)
    - Irish Question (Box 2)
    - Isaiah 32:17 (Box 2)
    - Isaiah 40:31 (Box 2)
    - John 1:14 (Box 2)
    - John 6:12b (Box 2)
    - John 10:10 (Box 2)
    - John 12:26 (Box 2)
    - John 15:26-27 (Box 2)
    - I Kings 20:28 (Box 2)
    - Let this Mind Be in You Which Has Also in Christ Jesus (Phil. 2:5) (Box 2)
    - Luke 19:41-44 (Box 2)
    - Mark 9:29 (Box 2)
    - Mark 15:54 (Box 2)
    - Matthew 7:24-29 (Box 2)
    - Matthew 21:23-27 (Box 2)
    - Nehemiah 4:18 (Box 2)
    - Numbers 23:13 (Box 2)
    - The Purpose of Religion - The Unprofitable Servant (Box 2)
    - Religion in the Home (Box 2)
    - Revelation 21:17b (Box 2)
    - Romans 1:16a (Box 2)
    - Romans 16:5 and I Timothy 3:15 (Box 2)
    - The Shadow of Peter: Acts (Box 2)
    - The Simplicity that is in Christ. The Simplicity that is towards Christ (II Cor. 11:3) (Box 2)
    - Thy Will Be Done (Box 2)
    - I Timothy 3:15 (Box 2)
    - II Timothy 1:6-7 (Palm Sunday talk to confirmation class) (Box 2)
    - The Unknown Self (Box 2)
    - Wealth - Produced, Predatory and [?] (Box 2)
    - Zechariah 9:9 (Box 2)
    - Fragmentary, untitled and/or undated, 3 folders (Box 2)
- Lectures
  The Lecture series consists of the Fellowship series of lectures that Williams was working on at the time of his death. This series is significant because of its amplification of Williams' view on race relations, industrial relations, and relations among nations.
  - Fellowship series
    - Fellowship in industry (Box 2)
    - Fellowship between the races (Box 2)
    - Fellowship between the nations (Box 2)
    - The gospel of fellowship (Box 2)
- Journals (some include selected typescripts)
  Of particular interest for their expatiation of Williams' liberal theology are a run of journals that Williams kept while attending different conferences and while participating in activities that took him away from his Detroit base. This Journals series includes selected typescripts compiled by Williams family members that make examination easier. The researcher will find of interest that journal written while attending a seminar on the English labor party in 1921.
  - Trip to Europe 1896 (Box 2)
  - Lambeth Conference; trip to England, Wales, Scotland, etc. 1908 (Box 2)
  - Red Cross Mission to France 1917 (Box 2)
  - Lambeth Conference 1921 (Box 2)
  - Seminar on the English Labor Party 1921, 3 folders (Box 2)
    (also notes on seminar and clippings)
- Events
  The Events series contains materials from special church related events in which Williams participated.
  - Episcopal Convention (Boston) October 1904 (Box 2)
    (scrapbook of clippings)
  - Consecration of CDW as bishop 1906 (Box 2)
  - St. Paul's Cathedral cornerstone laying 1908 (Box 2)
  - Annual sessions of Protestant Episcopal Church (Detroit) April-May 1908 (Box 2)
  - Lambeth Conferences 1908, circa 1916, 1920 (Box 2)
  - Special events, programs, invitations, etc (Box 2)
- Obituaries, condolences, etc.
  The Obituaries, Condolences, etc. series obituaries of Charles D. Williams and extensive file of letters of condolence to this family from friends and prominent clergymen, including Reinhold Niehbur.
  - Memorial services 1923 and post-1923 (scattered) (Box 3)
  - Memorial addresses (Box 3)
  - Obituaries from various periodicals (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook of obituaries (Box 3)
  - Letters of sympathy 1923, 5 folders (Box 3)
    (include Reinhold Niebuhr letter)
- Various
  The Various series is composed of scrapbooks and clippings about Williams career, and a variety of collected material by family members.
  - Scrapbook 1905-1921 (scattered) (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook 1908-1910 (Box 3)
  - Clippings (before 1923) (Box 3)
  - Clippings (post-1923) (Box 3)
  - Lucy Williams letters (Box 3)
  - Williams family (Box 3)
    (selected transcripts of various family member journals)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Published writings (articles, sermons, etc.), 2 expandable folders (Box 3)
- Photographs
  The collection concludes with two envelopes of Photographs, mainly portraits of Williams, photos of churches where he ministered, and a few portraits of family members.
  - Portraits (Box 3)
  - Family and friends; church buildings (Box 3)
Related Material
Two books written by Williams are available in the library's book collection. These volumes are The Christian Ministry and Social Problems (1917) and A Valid Christianity for to-day (1909).